<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The examination, confession, and condemnation of Henry Robson fisherman of Rye, who poysoned his wife in the strangest maner that euer hitherto hath bin heard of.</title>
            <author>Robson, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114565</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849790</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849790</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14958</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14958)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1558:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The examination, confession, and condemnation of Henry Robson fisherman of Rye, who poysoned his wife in the strangest maner that euer hitherto hath bin heard of.</title>
                  <author>Robson, Henry.</author>
                  <author>L. B., 16th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Felix Kyngston for R. VV[alker] and are to be solde in Paternoster row at the signe of the Talbot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The arraignment of Henry Robson.</note>
                  <note>Epistle to the reader signed: L.B.</note>
                  <note>Publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B²  (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Robson, Henry.</term>
               <term>Trials (Murder) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14958:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14958:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE EXAMINA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, confeſsion, and condemnation of <hi>Henry Robſon Fiſherman of</hi> Rye,
<hi>who poyſoned his</hi> wife in the ſtrangeſt maner that euer hitherto hath bin heard
of.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by Felix Kingſton for <hi>R. VV.</hi> and are to be ſolde in
Paternoſter row at the ſigne of the Talbot. 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14958:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GEntle Readers, amongſt all the cruell Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, poyſonings and homicides, I haue here
deſcribed one, which in my iudgement paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all that euer were inuented; together with Gods
prouidence in bringing it to light. And the ſooner haue I penned it, that others may beware of
being deceiued by Sathan to doe the like, in hope it ſhall be concealed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>L. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:14958:2"/>
            <head>The examination, confeſsion, and <hi>condemnation of</hi> Henry Robſon
<hi>Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> of <hi>Rye,</hi> who poyſoned his wife in the ſtrangeſt maner that euer
hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath been heard of.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T Rye in Suſſex there dwelled a man whoſe name was <hi>Henrie Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> by trade
he vſed fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and liued long time in very good eſtimation amongſt his neighbors, till
ſuch time as through his lauiſh ſpending, he came greatly in debt, to his vtter ruine. For
when <hi>Lucifer</hi> had found a meanes how to accompliſh his will, he neuer left him til by his
diuilliſh practiſes he had brought him to the gallowes. For hauing liued there, and being
happened into the danger of the law, his Creditors began to put him in ſuite: whom when he could
no waies ſatiſfie, he was caſt into priſon, where he long time remained languiſhing in
woe. This <hi>Robſon</hi> had a wife, who for her honeſt
<pb facs="tcp:14958:3"/>
dealing &amp; good neighbourhood, was greatly beloued both of yong and old. And although ſhe
could no waies redeeme him, yet did ſhe relieue him in ſuch ſort by her diligent labor. that
each one wondered at her indeuour: yet neuertheleſſe, he little weighed neither her kindnes nor
the lawes of God, as hereafter ſhall manifeſtly appeare: but deuiſed conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually how he
might make her away: who being dead, he determined to ſell al that euer he could make, and being
redeemed out of priſon, to haue conuaied himſelfe ouer into the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and
there to haue liued.</p>
            <p>Whileſt theſe miſchieuous thoughts har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in his minde, the diuell ſtirred vp the
minde of one <hi>Glaſier,</hi> being then in priſon, to be an inſtrument to put this his
villanie in practiſe: who one day finding a fit oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, he thus began. Faith <hi>Harry</hi>
I am ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to ſee thee liue thus in priſon, and haſt been ſo well beloued in this towne.
Tuſh <hi>Glaſier</hi> (ſayd this <hi>Robſon)</hi> tis too late now to bee ſorie, when
there is no remedie: for ſo long as my wife liueth, it is vnpoſſible that euer I ſhould
come out. Faith then ſaid <hi>Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier)</hi> ſure if my wifes death could procure my
libertie. I would neuer be in bondage, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned. No (ſayd <hi>Robſon)</hi> why my
wiſhes can neuer the ſooner procure her death. I but (ſaid the other) your indeuour may,
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:14958:3"/>
being once ſuſpected: and if you wil take my counſell and be ſecret, I will warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you
ſhe ſhall not long liue. Which words, when <hi>Robſon</hi> heard, greatly reioycing at this
good hap, he not onely vowed to be ſecret, but alſo to put this in ſpeedie execution, and
during life to remaine <hi>Glaſiers</hi> friend, if it ſorted to good effect. In ſhort time
after <hi>Glaſier</hi> was deliuered: at which inſtant <hi>Robſon</hi> put him in minde of
his promiſe, which he promiſed preſently to accompliſh. And haſting downe to one
<hi>Fiſhers</hi> a Mercer in the towne, bought a peniworth of Ratſbane; and comming to the
priſon againe, in ſecret he deliuered it to <hi>Robſon,</hi> willing him to temper it with
glaſſe ſmall beaten, and wrapt in the ſkinne of a ſhoulder of mutton, to the quantity of
a haſle nut, or leſſe, and in the night when his wife ſhould next come to lie with him, he
ſhould conuey it into her priuie parts, which hee would warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without danger to him ſhuld kil
her: and ſo he departed. O hainous crime and wicked counſell, the like whereof ſince
<hi>Cain</hi> murthered the righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> hath not been heard of. But now marke the
euent: ſome ſeauen daies after his wife (according to her accuſtomed order) came to the
priſon, and finding her welbeloued huſband, ſhe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted him ioying of his welfare. But he
who minded nought els but murther, ſaluted her
<pb facs="tcp:14958:4"/>
with a diſſembling ſhew of friendſhip: and at night when ſhe would haue departed, hee
conſtrained her to ſtay all night, which was the deareſt nights pleaſure that euer woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
had: for in the night hee put in practiſe his former imaginations: which how it worked ſhall
hereafter be declared. In the morning without ſuſpect, the poore ſillie woman de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting
home, little thinking her death ſhuld ſo ſoone approch, falling cloſe to her worke, ſhe
found her ſelfe grieued, and her bodie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſwell more and more. For now it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to
runne and eate into her vaines, ſo that with the extreame paine ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to goe
to bed, where ſhe lay lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing ſome fiue daies. Her neighbours reſorting ſtill to
comfort her, and many Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions were ſent for, all which agreed that ſhe was poyſoned.
And therefore gaue her many purgations, and vſing many other meanes, but all could not ſerue:
for in their liues they had neuer ſeene nor heard of ſo ſtrange an accident. When they had
vſed all the meanes they could, her daies of life being now finiſhed, ſhe tooke her laſt
adieu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the world, and ſo dyed. So ſoone as
ſhe was dead, according to the maner, they would haue prepared for her buriall: but the
Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions hindered their purpoſe, and hauing obtained licenſe of the officers, they
cauſed
<pb facs="tcp:14958:4"/>
her to bee ripped, where they found in euerie vaine both glaſſe and Ratſbane, and yet could
not deuiſe how or by what meanes it ſhould come thither: for that it could not be, it ſhould
there happen by any conueiance in meate or drinke: and therefore they determined to finde out by
ſome meanes who was the doer of this villany. And incontiuently, ſending to euery ſhop in the
towne to know who lately bought any Ratſbane; at the ſayd <hi>Fiſhers</hi> (aforeſayd) they
heard that one <hi>Glaſier</hi> two weekes before had there bought a peniworth. Whereupon they
made ſearch for the ſaid <hi>Glaſier:</hi> but he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing heard of this newes, and knowing
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe guiltie of the crime, was fled away. Then they bethought how <hi>Glaſier</hi> was
then lately returned out of priſon where <hi>Robſon</hi> was, whoſe wife it was that was
poiſoned. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring further when <hi>Robſons</hi> wife was with him in priſon, they
learned that ſhe lay with him in the priſon houſe not full a weeke before. This all being put
together, they began to coniecture of the matter: and the Maior, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats and Recorder being
aſſembled, they ſent for <hi>Robſon,</hi> who incontinent was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: and
being come, the Recorder (one maſter <hi>Boulton)</hi> began thus.</p>
            <p>Neighbour <hi>Robſon</hi> (ſayd he) we vnderſtand by one <hi>Glaſier,</hi> that you had
certaine poyſon of him which you cauſed him to buy; now wee haue ſent for you to know to what
intent you
<pb facs="tcp:14958:5"/>
bought it: for that you are ſuſpected of the death of your wife, and by ſome manifeſtly
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed. Which he hearing, began to vſe many proteſtations, that he was as ignorant both of
any ſuch poyſon, or of the deede, as the childe newly borne. Nay (ſayd the Recorder) if you
be ſo obſtinate, we will bring <hi>Glaſier</hi> forth, who to your ſhame ſhal teſtifie
it, and then you are not onely guiltie of the poyſon, but alſo of the act doing: and therefore
confeſſe the truth &amp; ſhame the deuill. Well (ſayd <hi>Robſon)</hi> I had indeede
Ratſbane: but what of that? Why didſt thou deny it then (ſayd the Recorder?) it ſhewes a
guiltie conſcience. But what didſt thou with it, and to what intent didſt thou buy it? Why
(ſayd he) the Courthouſe is full of Rats, and I bought it to kill them. That is not ſo
(ſaid the Recorder) but the deuill is the father of lyers, and I feare thou art his ſonne:
confeſſe the trueth what thou didſt with it. Well (ſayd <hi>Robſon)</hi> if you will
needes know, I will trulie reſolue you. I haue been long in priſon, and I haue often heard that
poyſon will breake open any iron lock, and therfore I bought it, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby to get my
libertie. Now I haue told the truth I hope you will pardon me. No (ſayd the Recorder) thou haſt
not told y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth: for with it and glaſſe mingled together thou didſt poyſon thy wife: and
therefore as thou lookeſt for any fauour at our hands, confeſſe how, and in what maner thou
didſt it, and who
<pb facs="tcp:14958:5"/>
was thy connſeller in it. Well, then I perceiue (ſayd <hi>Robſon)</hi> you glut after my
blood, and if it will pleaſure you you ſhall haue it. For they hauing told him truth, he could
no longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it: and therfore imagining that <hi>Glaſier</hi> was taken and had confeſt al,
he openly declared the whole maner aforeſayd, how and in what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hee had done it, and for
what cauſe, and who was his counſeller: which they hearing greatly marueiled. And ſo for that
time hee was committed to priſon, where he remained til the Seſſions day, where he was
arraigned and condemned, and according to the law hee was there adiudged to be hanged, which was
performed.</p>
            <p>The Lord of his inſinit grace graunt euery one better to withſtand Sathans temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and
eſehew his ſubtilties, that they be not led by his allurements, nor intrapped in his ſnares,
who ſeeketh by all means to bring euery one to confuſion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
